だが 金時の…＞
この世のすべてを恨んだ｡
♪♪～
((金時:だったら ﾕｰ
整形しちゃいなよ))
謎のﾌﾟｰﾀﾛｰ 坂田金時と➡
今は 昔の話だ｡
ｵﾚが ﾅﾝﾊﾞｰﾜﾝﾎｽﾄに
なれなかった理由➡
ｵﾚは こんなｱｺﾞに生まれた
運命を呪い➡
今は 異国ﾎｽﾄたちの言葉が
飛び交う｡
かつて 和製ﾎｽﾄが夢を馳せた
新宿の空には➡
＜新八:ﾎｽﾄの国 ｵﾚたちの街が
そう呼ばれていたのは➡
しかし そこに男が２人｡
＜ そう… すべては
このｹﾂｱｺﾞが悪かったんだ｡
かつてのﾅﾝﾊﾞｰﾜﾝﾎｽﾄだった
ｹﾂｱｺﾞ新八｡
それは このｹﾂのように割れた
ｱｺﾞだったんだ｡
今 ２人が 汚れた夜の街を
駆け抜ける＞
＜ その ひと言で目が覚めた｡
そう 解決策は
あまりにも簡単に そこにあった＞
[Note: Spoof of Episode 3.]
The land of the host.
There was a time, long ago, when our town was called by that name.
Those dream-filled Shinjuku skies upon which Japanese hosts once gazed on their dreams...
are now filled with words by hosts from foreign countries.
(神楽)よかったわね 新八｡
手術は 無事 成功したみたいよ｡
However, there were two men.
The enigmatic vagrant, Kintoki Sakata,
どうした？
早く包帯とってみろよ｡
and the former number one host, Shinpachi Buttchin.
いや… やっぱ ｵﾚ
ちょっと不安で➡
ちゃんと
生まれ変われたのかなって…｡
The two of them still run in this corrupt night town.
[Kintama]
♪♪～
Yes...
It was all this buttchin's fault.
The reason I couldn't become the number one host...
ど… どうですか？ ｵﾚのｱｺﾞ｡
That would be this chin, which looked like a buttcrack.
ﾌｯ… ﾊﾞｯﾁﾘだ｡
最近の整形は ﾊﾟﾈｪわ｡
I cursed fate for bringing me into this infernal world with such a chin,
これで自分で見てみたら？
and blamed everything on this world.
But Kintoki said...
You, then...
[Note: From popular phrase by CEO of Johnny's Entertainment, Johnny Kitagawa.]
ﾎﾝﾄだ… ｹﾂｱｺﾞじゃなくなってる｡
Get a chin job.
His words woke me up.
ｵﾚのｱｺﾞ… ｹﾂじゃなくて➡
Yes...
There was a simple solution.
前に… って えぇ～!!
[Final Episode]
I'm happy for you, Shinpachi.
The surgery was a success.
What's wrong?
Take the bandages off already.
Well, I'm a little worried...
Wondering if I've actually been reborn...
H-How does my chin look?
Perfect.
Plastic surgery these days is crazy stuff.
[Note: Kintoki is talking like kids in Shibuya.]
Why don't you take a look yourself?
It's true...
I no longer have a buttchin.
My chin no longer looks like a butt...
It looks like the front.
[Fin]
[Sweet Shop: sweets and cake]
(お妙)あの すみません｡
頼んでたｹｰｷ できました？
Um, excuse me.
Is the cake I ordered ready?
ああ おねえちゃん
ちょっと待ってね｡
Oh, little lady.
Hold on a moment.
Here, it's done.
[Note: On cake: "Happy Birthday Kyu-chan."]
ほら できてるよ｡
わぁ！
ｽﾃｷじゃないですか 姉上｡
Doesn't it look great, Sis?
これは きっと
九兵衛さんも喜んでくれますよ｡
I'm sure Kyubei-san will love it.
そうね｡
おじさん ありがとうございます｡
That's right.
Thanks so much, Mister.
まいど｡
Come again.
それにしても
誕生日会なんて行くの➡
Still, I wonder how many years it's been since I went to a birthday party.
何年ぶりだろう｡
I'm getting all excited, even though it isn't my birthday.
自分の誕生日でもないのに
なんだか ﾄﾞｷﾄﾞｷしてきましたよ｡
That's right.
そうね｡ 私たち基本ｻｻｴさん方式で
歳をとらないから➡
[Note: From Sazae-san series, where characters don't age.]
We don't actually age, a la the Sazae-san system,
お誕生日会なんて
したくても できないものね｡
so we couldn't have birthday parties if we wanted to.
Sis, please stop saying things like that.
姉上 やめてください｡
そういう発言は…｡
今日は 私たち➡
Today, we aren't just celebrating this birthday for Kyu-chan,
そして
ｻｻｴさんたちの分も含めて➡
九ちゃんを
お祝いしてあげましょう｡
but for the rest of us and the members of Sazae-san as well.
["That Person Looks Different From Usual During A Birthday Party."]
そういえば 銀さんたちは？
Come to think of it, where's Gin-san and everyone else?
ああ ﾌﾟﾚｾﾞﾝﾄを買ってから来るって｡
They'll come after they buy presents.
Will they be all right?
大丈夫かしら？ 変なもの
買ってこなきゃいいけど…｡
I hope they don't buy anything strange.
(東城)お妙殿！ 新八殿！
Otae-dono.
Shinpachi-dono.
Tojo-san, what are you doing there?
東城さん 何やってんですか
そんなところで｡
Shh.
(東城)
ｼｰｯ！ 早くこっち こっち！
Hurry! Over here!
It'll be a problem if you enter through the front door right out in the open!
困りますよ｡ そんな堂々と
門前から入ってこられちゃ！
この度の柳生九兵衛生誕祭は➡
The celebration of Kyubei Yagyu's birthday was a surprise I planned in secret.
若をびっくりさせようと
私が内緒で計画したものなのです｡
若は 出稽古でまだ
お戻りになっていないとはいえ➡
Though the young master is out training,
慎重を期し裏口から
お入りいただけますか｡
we should be careful and enter through the back door.
Ah, I see.
ああ そうなんだ｡ 九兵衛さん
知らないんだ｡ 確かに…｡
Kyubei-san doesn't know about this.
Makes sense...
((九兵衛:誕生日会？
そんなくだらんもの必要ない))
A birthday party?
Who needs that crap?
とか いいそうだもんね｡
Would be her likely response.
こちらのほうは 今日の
ﾌﾟﾛｸﾞﾗﾑになっておりますので➡
These are the programs for today's event, so please flip through them.
確認しておいてくだされ｡
And a script has been prepared,
あとは こちらの台本のほうも➡
ｾﾘﾌなどあらかじめ
決めておきましたので➡
so please memorize your lines before the young master returns.
若が来るまでに
覚えておいてくだされ｡
台本？ そんなのあんの？
どんだけ張り切ってんですかｱﾝﾀ！
A script?! You've got a script?!
How excited about this are you?!
ｱﾄﾞﾘﾌﾞとか
余計なことは必要ないので➡
There's no need for any ad-libbing or the like, so please stick to the script.
この台本どおりに
行動してくださいね｡
U-Uh, Tojo-san?
あ あの東城さん！
張り切るのもわかるけど➡
I know that you're excited,
こう堅苦しくちゃ
せっかくの楽しいお誕生日会も…｡
but the birthday party won't be any fun if you're so strict about it...
新ちゃん 新ちゃん！
えっ？
Shin-chan. Shin-chan.
Look over there.
見てよ あれ｡ あの人
どこかで見たことがない？
Doesn't that person look familiar?
ん？ あっ！ あれ俳優の
小栗旬之助じゃないですか！
Isn't that the actor, Shunnosuke Oguri?!
[Note: From popular young actor, Shun Oguri.]
What is a red-hot actor doing in this place?!
何で今 人気絶頂の
俳優がこんなところに！
もちろん
若の生誕祭にご招待したのです｡
Of course, I invited him to the celebration of our young master's birth.
えっ！
新ちゃん あそこに歩いてる人も｡
Shin-chan, the person over there, too.
あっ 多毛さんだ！
お昼の顔 多毛さんだ！
Whoa! It's Tamo-san!
A big name in daytime television!
もしかして あれも…｡
言わずもがな｡
Is he also...
Obviously.
名門 柳生家の跡取りたる
若の生誕祭ですから｡
This is a celebration of the birth of the young master of the famous Yagyu clan,
これくらいは至極当然のこと｡
so this is only natural.
あ～ な なんてこった！
I-Incredible...
芸能界 政界あらゆる分野の
著名人があっちにも こっちにも！
Celebrities from entertainment and political circles are all over the place!
これが柳生家の力｡将軍家指南役を
仰せつかっていた ｾﾚﾌﾞの力｡
This is the power of the Yagyu clan...
The power of the famous, appointed instructors for the Shogun's household!
We'll be using ocean shrimp and oysters, marinated in Chat Filhot, cooked a la Provence with a thick sauce.
[Note: In French.]
Yes, sir.
まあ 大変！ こんなにたくさんの
人が招待されていたなんて｡
Oh no.
I had no idea so many people were invited.
あのｹｰｷをどうわけようかしら？
How will we cut the cake?
ｻｲｺﾛｽﾃｰｷくらいの
大きさになってしまうわ｡
We'll end up with slices the size of little steak cubes.
言ってる場合ですか 姉上！
ﾎﾞｸら 完全に場違いですよ！
Is this the time to be talking about that, Sis?!
We're completely out of place here!
明らかに浮いてますよ！
お誕生日会なんていうから➡
Like we don't belong here.
I dressed casually since I heard it was a birthday party...
気軽に来たら これ全然そういう➡
But this isn't anything cozy like that!
ｱｯﾄﾎｰﾑな感じじゃ
ないじゃないですか！
若のご友人ゆえ
特別にご招待しましたが➡
You were invited as friends of the young master,
あなたたちは本来 ここに
立ち入ることすら許されない身分｡
but under normal circumstances, people of your status would not be admitted.
Just stick to the script, keep your mouths shut, and stay in your seats.
台本どおりに騒がず 黙って➡
席にお座りになられていれば
それでいいですから｡
とにかく 目立たぬように
場の空気を壊さぬように➡
Refrain from any actions that would be conspicuous or ruin the mood.
つつしんで行動してくだされ｡
くれぐれも 若に恥を
かかさぬようにお願いしますよ｡
Do not shame the young master.
私は 若を呼んでくるので
あとはお願いしますね｡
I'll go get the young master now.
姉上 早く
銀さんたちと合流しましょう｡
Sis, we need to meet up with Gin-san and everyone else.
彼らをこんなところに
野放しにしていれば➡
If we let them run around this place unsupervised, all hell will break loose.
とんでもないことになります｡
You don't need to worry about that.
そんな心配しなくても大丈夫よ｡
ＴＰＯくらいわきまえてるわよ
銀さんたちも｡
They know to behave appropriately for the situation.
Ah, they're over there.
あっ いた あそこ！ ほら！
See. They're sitting quietly in their seats.
ちゃんとおとなしく
席に座ってるじゃない｡
ﾎﾝﾄだ よかった｡
You're right. That's a relief.
何かやらかす前に
間に合ったみたいです｡
Guess we found them before they had time to do anything.
長谷川さんに 桂さん｡
Hasegawa-san and Katsura-san.
竜宮城にいた
ﾒﾝﾊﾞｰも呼ばれてるみたいね｡
I guess the people who went to Ryugu Castle were invited.
[Note: From Eps.115-118.]
ほら 律儀に亀梨さんの甲羅まで｡
See? Even Kamenashi-san's shell is here.
[Note: He appeared in Eps.115-118.]
本体は消えちゃったのかしら？
I wonder if his actual body disappeared.
不気味なこと言わないでください｡
Don't say creepy stuff like that.
奥さんがまた出産とかじゃ｡
His wife might be giving birth again...
[Note: The body of Kamenashi's wife disappeared so she looked like a skeleton during her pregnancy in Ep. 115-116.]
それにしても なんか みんな
異様に神妙な顔してませんか？
Still, everybody seems oddly serious.
(お妙)緊張してるんじゃない？
周りが有名人だらけだから｡
Maybe they're nervous?
Since they're surrounded by celebrities.
なんか変ですよ 何やって…｡
Something's odd.
What are they doing...?
(長谷川)５！
１ ２ ３ ４ ５！
Five!
One, two, three, four, five!
よっしゃあ！
人気俳優になり➡
Booya!
I become a popular actor and my income goes up twenty million!
収入 2,000万増える！
以後 順番が回ってくるごとに
2,000万入る｡
I get twenty million every time I circle the board now!
勝った～！
これは完全に勝ったな｡
I've won!
I've undeniably won!
勝ち組みだ
勝ち組みの仲間入りだよ｡
I'm a winner!
I've become a winner!
Finally...!
ついに ｵﾚも…｡
(桂)黙れ！
Shut up!
勝負は 最後までわからんぞ！
This isn't over until the end!
いいや 勝ったね
ここから ｷﾐたち負け組みが➡
No, I've won!
You losers will never be able to catch up!
追いつくことは
到底 不可能｡
だって 俳優だもの
勝ち組みだもの｡
Because I'm an actor! A winner!
(銀時)ﾎﾞｰﾄﾞの上ではな｡
いくら 金持ちになろうと➡
On the game board, sure.
Even if you're rich in the game,
現実という名のﾎﾞｰﾄﾞの上では
ｱﾝﾀが無職という事実は➡
don't forget that it doesn't change the fact
that you're unemployed in real life, dumbass.
なんら変わりねえことを
忘れんなよ この野郎｡
そこまで言わなくても
いいんじゃねえの？
You didn't have to mention that!
ｹﾞｰﾑくらい夢見させてくれても
いいんじゃねえの？
Can't you let me dream when we're playing a game?!
黙れ ﾏﾀﾞｵ｡ 振り出しから➡
Shove it, DORK.
A person who hasn't worked a second in his entire life shouldn't get cocky.
まんじりとも動けねえ
人生を送ってるくせに➡
調子にのんなよ｡
なにを!?
What's that?!
ｹﾞｰﾑでも現実でも負け組みの
お前らよりはﾏｼなんだよ！
At least I'm not a loser in both the game and real life, like you guys!
(桂)ｷｻﾏ そこまで言うか！
そこに直れ 叩き斬ってくれる｡
That's going too far!
Get down on your knees!
I'll cut you down!
あぁ～!! 何すんだ 新八君｡
What are you doing, Shinpachi-kun?!
せっかく
人気俳優になれたのに｡
I just became a popular actor!
何すんだじゃねえだろ｡
Don't give me that.
I was wondering why you guys were so serious...
珍しく神妙な顔してると
思ったら➡
お前 なんつうとこで
人生すごろくやってんだ｡
Why are you playing the Game of Life in this place?!
What are you talking about, Shinpachi?
何言ってんだ 新八｡
あ？
お誕生日会に 人生すごろくは
必要不可欠だろうが｡
The Game of Life is an essential part of celebrating birthdays.
ふだんなら みんな集まって➡
Normally, everybody immediately engages in the unhealthy habit of playing video games,
不健康に
即ﾃﾚﾋﾞｹﾞｰﾑってところだが➡
お誕生日会は ご馳走を
作ってくれる お母さんの目が➡
but during a birthday party, the mother making the food is keeping a sharp watch.
いつもより光っている｡
So everybody gives up on video games
そこで ﾃﾚﾋﾞｹﾞｰﾑはあきらめ➡
人生すごろくあたりで手を打って
ちょっといい子ぶり➡
and pretends to be good children by playing board games like Life.
ご馳走にありつく｡
So they can eat good food!
これが お誕生日会の
極意だろうが｡
This is the principle of the birthday party.
うおぉ～！
知らねえんだよ！
I don't give a damn about the worthless birthday knowledge you've assembled!
ﾃﾒｴらが培ったきた しようもねえ
お誕生日会ﾉｳﾊｳなんて｡
新八君 ことは
ご馳走の問題ではないのだ｡
Shinpachi-kun, the food isn't the issue.
ここで お母さんの機嫌を
損ねれば➡
If you offend the mother,
誕生日会のあと 九兵衛君が➡
there's a possibility that she won't buy Kyubei-kun a Nintendo game afterwards.
ﾌｧﾐｺﾝのｶｾｯﾄを買ってもらえない
という危険性が出てくる｡
And our dreams of gathering at Kyubei-kun's place after school to play RBI Baseball will be shattered.
[Note: Popular baseball game from the 80s.]
しいては 放課後
九兵衛君の家に集まって➡
みんなで ｢ﾌｧﾐｽﾀ｣という
ｵﾚたちの夢も➡
跡形もなく四散する｡
そんな夢
抱いた覚えねえんだけど！
I don't remember having that dream, ever!
つうか ｵﾒｴら さっきから
どんだけﾌｧﾐｺﾝやりてえんだよ｡
And what's with your obsession with playing Nintendo?!
童心に帰りすぎだっつうの！
You've gone way back to being little kids!
お母さんなんて
どこにもいませんよ｡
The mom isn't even here!
[Note: Because Kyubei's mom is dead.]
光ってんのは
お母さんの目じゃなくて➡
And the sharp eyes staring at us belong to all the celebrities, not the mom!
ｾﾚﾌﾞたちの目です！
ここは ﾎﾞｸらが子供の頃やってた➡
This isn't like the birthday parties we held as children!
誕生日会とは違うんですよ｡
Get a clue!
空気読んでください 空気！
いや 何あれ ちょっと｡
Ew, what is that?
Are they acquaintances of Kyubei-dono?
ひょっとして 彼らも
九兵衛殿の知り合いなのか｡
まさか そんな｡
No way...
くっ… 小栗旬之助
こっち ｶﾞﾝ見じゃないですか｡
Shunnosuke Oguri is staring right at us!
曇りなき眼で
こっち ｶﾞﾝ見じゃないですか｡
He's not even trying to hide it!
ﾎﾞｸら 九兵衛さんの
友人代表なんですよ｡
We're here as Kyubei-san's friends!
ﾎﾞｸらがおかしなことしたら
九兵衛さんに恥かかせるんですよ｡
If we do anything weird, it'll shame Kyubei-san!
心配いらねえ｡
You don't need to worry.
ｵﾚたちは 幼い頃から
あらゆるお誕生日会に顔を出し➡
Through the years, we've been to many birthday parties and eaten lots of food.
ご馳走を食らってきた
いわば 誕生日会のﾌﾟﾛﾌｪｯｼｮﾅﾙ｡
You could call us birthday party professionals...
Birthday Fighters.
[Note: Caption on the top looks like Saint Seiya: Knights of the Zodiac title logo.]
(３人)ﾊﾞｰｽﾃﾞｰﾌｧｲﾀｰだ｡
ﾀﾀﾞ飯たかりに
行ってただけだろうが！
You only go for the free food!
Birthday Fighters don't do anything to make the birthday boy or girl look bad.
誕生日闘士は
お誕生日会の主役の顔を➡
潰すようなﾏﾈは まずしない｡
ふだん 学校で
多少いじられてたり➡
Even if it's someone weak, who usually gets bullied at school,
弱い立場だったりするﾔﾂでも➡
you make them look good in front of their mother.
お母さんの前では
必ず立てる｡ これは鉄則だ｡
This is an absolute rule.
そうすることによって➡
By doing that,
ｱｲﾂを呼んだら楽しい
などという評価が広まり➡
you earn the reputation of a person who makes birthday parties more fun.
後々のお誕生日会に
つながるからな｡
That leads to invitations to more birthday parties.
ゆえに お母さんにだけ
なんか強気｡
So you must not mouth off to the mother.
家に入ったら
玄関から もう便所くさい➡
Even if you enter the house and find that it smells like a restroom,
などという弱点を見つけても➡
これを
絶対に口外することはしない｡
you must never mention that fact.
信用に関わるからな｡
Because it'll affect their trust in you.
まあ まず ｵﾚたちに
任せておけば大丈夫だ 安心しろ｡
You won't have to worry if you leave it to us.
Relax.
今回は 他校の知らない生徒も
招待されている｡
Students from other schools have also been invited this time.
Ｂ２ﾊﾟﾀｰﾝだな｡
至急 ﾃﾞｰﾀの算出を頼む｡
Pattern B-2.
Compute their data, stat.
(長谷川/桂)ﾗｼﾞｬｰ｡
ﾊﾞｶだろ ｵﾒｴら!!
Roger.
You're all idiots!
Your presence here is making Kyubei-san look bad!
ｵﾒｴら自体が
九兵衛さんの顔を潰してんだよ！
お前ら自体が便所くさいんだよ！
You're the ones who smell like restrooms!
余計なことをしなくても➡
You don't have to do anything. There will still be plenty to eat.
ご馳走なんて
いくらでもありつけますよ｡
ﾊﾞｲｷﾝｸﾞ形式なんですよ
このﾊﾟｰﾃｨｰは｡
This party is a buffet.
Once the party's started, you can eat all the food you want.
ﾊﾟｰﾃｨｰが始まれば
あそこに並んでる料理を➡
いくらでも食べ放題ですよ｡
だから おとなしく…｡
So behave...
ちょっと 何？ あのﾃﾝﾄ｡
Hey, what's with that tent?
なんで あんなところに
ﾃﾝﾄが張ってあるの？
Why is there a tent in that place?
あれじゃ ｼﾞｬﾏで
食事を取りにいけないじゃない｡
That'll prevent us from getting food.
なんなの？ あれ｡
登山家でも来てるの？
What is that?
Is there a mountain climber among the guests?
まだｱﾙか？ ﾊﾟｰﾃｨｰ開始時刻は｡
The party hasn't started yet?
なに
徹夜覚悟の構えで並んでんだ!!
Why are you acting like someone lined up for an overnight release?!
ﾊﾞｲｷﾝｸﾞごときで
どこまで体 張ってんだよ！
Why are you putting your body on the line for a buffet?!
体じゃなく ﾃﾝﾄ張ってるだけｱﾙ｡
I put a tent up to mark my place in line, not my body.
うめえこと言ってんじゃねえよ！
腹立つ！
Stop trying to be funny! That pisses me off!
いいから 席 戻れ！ 恥ずかしい!!
Just go back to your seat! This is embarrassing!
そんなに必死にならないでも
ちゃんと ご馳走 回ってくるから｡
You don't have to try so hard. There will still be plenty to eat.
そんな卑しい人
ここにいないから！
The people here aren't that greedy.
ｲﾔある！ こんなに
たくさんいるんだよ？
No way!
Look at all the people here!
きっと 私の春巻も
なくなってしまう｡
My spring rolls will be all gone!
なくなってしまうね！
永住するｱﾙ！
All gone!
I'm staying here forever!
春巻が食べ放題なら
私 ここで春を越す！
I'll stay all spring if that's what it takes to eat all the spring rolls I want!
春でも秋でも
なんでも巻いてあげるからさ！
I'll give you all the spring rolls or fall rolls you want!
お願いだから 神楽ちゃん 戻ろう｡
Please go back to your seat!
こんなことしてたら
ﾎﾞｸら 追い出されちゃうよ!!
If you keep this up, they'll chase us out!
ほら みんなに
笑われてるよ ﾎﾞｸたち！
Come on!
Everybody's laughing at us!
ほら 見てみなよ｡
小栗君も こっち見…｡
See? Look.
Even Oguri-kun is looking...
小栗君も並ぼうとしてた…｡
Oguri-kun was getting in line!
He was definitely lined up like he thought it was okay to start eating!
今 完全に もう
料理 取っていいと勘違いして➡
小栗君も並ぼうとしてたよね!?
ﾁｯ…｡
Tsk.
まずいよ…
九兵衛さんだけじゃなく➡
This is bad.
Not only Kyubei-san, but now we've made Oguri-kun look bad, too!
小栗君にまで
恥かかせちゃったよ！
ﾊﾟｰﾃｨｰ お集まりの皆様
長らく お待たせいたしました｡
Hello, birthday guests.
Sorry for the long wait.
いよいよ 主役の到着です！
The birthday girl has finally arrived.
(九兵衛)なんだ？ 東城｡
いったい なんだというんだ？
What is it, Tojo?
What's going on?
(東城)いいから 若
早くお入りください｡
Just go in already, young master.
押すな ﾊﾞｶ者｡
Don't push me, fool.
いったい どうしたというの…｡
What's going on...?
(拍手)
(みんな)九兵衛さん
お誕生日 おめでとう!!
Kyubei-san, happy birthday!
これは…｡
Th... This is...
Kyu-chan's all surprised.
九ちゃんたら びっくりしてる｡
Gin-san, we're supposed to sing together now.
銀さん ここで大合唱らしいです｡
合唱？
Sing?
♪♪～
ほらほら これです｡
Here, here. This is it.
これ以上 周りから
浮くわけにはいきません｡
We can't stand out any further.
Let's try our best to sing along.
みんなで 一生懸命 歌いましょう｡
Happy birthday to you!
♪♪｢ﾊｯﾋﾟｰﾊﾞｰｽﾃﾞｰ ﾄｩ ﾕｰ｣
♪♪｢ﾊｯﾋﾟｰﾊﾞｰｽﾃﾞｰ ﾃﾞｨｱ 九兵衛｣
Happy birthday, dear Kyubei!
♪♪｢ﾊｯﾋﾟｰﾊﾞｰｽﾃﾞｰ ﾄｩ ﾕｰ
ﾊｯﾋﾟｰﾊﾞｰｽﾃﾞｰ ﾄｩ ﾕｰ｣
Happy birthday to you!
なんなの？ ちょっと あれ…｡
What was that...?
That was wretched.
完全に妨害してたわよね？ あれ｡
Honestly, what is he thinking?
ｲﾔね… 何 考えてんのかしら？
さっきから…｡
Huh? Why?
あれ なんで？
なんで余計浮いてんの？
Why am I standing out?
一生懸命歌ったのに…｡
17話 見ろ｡
I tried my best to sing along.
Go watch episode 17.
17話 見直してみろ｡
Go watch episode 17 again.
あっ やばいんですけど！
This is bad.
Tojo-san's slit eyes are wide open!
いつも糸目の東城さんの目が
見開かれてるんですけど｡
Staring over here without even blinking!
まばたきもせずに じっと
こっちを見てくるんですけど！
Happy birthday.
(みんな)おめでとう！
あ ありがとう ありがとう｡
Th-Thank you.
Thank you.
銀さん！ 今度は
花束 持ってくらしいです！
Gin-san.
We're supposed to take a bouquet over to her now.
It says that there's a bouquet under each table,
各ﾃｰﾌﾞﾙの下に 一束ずつ
花束があるんで 代表者が➡
so a representative from each table is supposed to take it to Kyubei-san.
それを 九兵衛さんに渡しに行けと
書いてありますよ｡
A representative...
代表者 仕方ない
ならば ｵﾚが行くしかあるまい｡
I suppose I have no choice.
I'll have to go.
For I am the only person here qualified to be the leader.
ﾘｰﾀﾞｰは ｵﾚしかありえんからな｡
ちょっと待つｱﾙ｡ お前 いつも➡
Hold it right there.
You always call me the leader.
私のこと ﾘｰﾀﾞｰ呼んでるｱﾙ｡
The leader of the leader is the real leader.
ﾘｰﾀﾞｰのﾘｰﾀﾞｰが
本物のﾘｰﾀﾞｰに決まりね！
Wait. Calm down, you two.
待て 落ち着け２人とも｡
This isn't the time to be fighting amongst ourselves.
今は 争ってる場合じゃねえだろ｡
As the elder, I should...
ここは 年長者のｵﾚがだな
代表して…｡
いや ｵﾚが行くと
言ってるだろう｡
No, I said I'm going.
No, I am!
(神楽)いや 私が行くね！
(長谷川)落ち着けよ ２人とも！
Calm down, you two!
ｵﾚが行けば
すべて丸く収まるじゃん！
Everything will be settled if I go!
(桂)ｵﾚが！
(長谷川)ｵﾚだって！
I can!
I am!
I will!
Ky-Kyu-chan, happy birthday.
きゅ 九ちゃん
誕生日おめでとう｡
はい｡
Here.
あ ありがとう｡
Th-Thanks...
Ew, what's with that?
ｲﾔだ 何あれ ちょっと
嫌がらせ？
Some type of harassment?
本当に さっきから
なんなの あの人たち｡
Honestly, what is wrong with that group?
What did they come here for?
何しに来てるの？
あっ！
銀さん やばいんですけど！
東城さんの目から ﾋﾞｰﾑが！
Gin-san! This is bad!
Tojo-san's eyes are going to shoot beams!
やばいです いいかげんにしないと
やばいです！
Very bad!
This will be very bad if we don't get our act together!
(拍手)
Um, I'm very surprised about all these people showing up so suddenly.
こんなにも大勢の方に
集まっていただき➡
急なことで ﾎﾞｸもまだ
驚いております｡
皆さん ﾎﾞｸのために➡
I'm very grateful that everyone came here for me.
今日は 本当に
ありがとうございました｡
Okay. Then we'll do presents before we start eating.
はい では会食の前に➡
ﾌﾟﾚｾﾞﾝﾄﾀｲﾑに
移らせていただきたいと思います｡
若に ﾌﾟﾚｾﾞﾝﾄなどがある人は
前のほうに出てきてください｡
Everyone with a present for the young master move forward.
はい はい はい!!
Yes, yes! Yes!
Sis! This is our chance to redeem ourselves!
姉上 ここで
名誉挽回するしかありません！
持っていきましょう
あのｹｰｷ ﾌﾟﾚｾﾞﾝﾄしてきましょう！
Let's take that cake to her!
As a present!
But they're all giving her incredible presents...
でも みんな あんなすごいものを
普通にﾌﾟﾚｾﾞﾝﾄしているのよ｡
Well, this is a key to our company's car. We would love the young master to use it...
我が社の車のｷｰなのですが ぜひ
若様に使っていただきたく…｡
こんな小さなｹｰｷ持っていくの
なんだか 恥ずかしくて｡
I'm kind of embarrassed to take such a small cake up there.
何言ってんですか！
九兵衛さんのために➡
What are you talking about?
You had this cake made for Kyubei-san, right?
作ってもらったｹｰｷでしょ
きっと喜びますよ！
I'm sure she'll love it.
そうだ ﾌﾟﾚｾﾞﾝﾄってのは
値段じゃねえぞ｡
That's right.
Presents aren't about price.
They're about feelings.
込めた気持が 大事なんだ｡
[Japanica Notebook]
[Note: From Japonica Notebook, popular notebook among kids. Costs approximately 100 yen ($1 USD).]
ｱﾝﾀのﾌﾟﾚｾﾞﾝﾄは
どこに気持が入ってんだよ!?
Where are the feelings in your present?
32ﾍﾟｰｼﾞあたりだな｡
知らねえよ！
Somewhere around the 32nd page.
How would I know that?!
ほら 行きましょう 姉上｡
Come on. Let's go, Sis.
It's bound to be better than this guy's present.
この人のよりは
絶対ﾏｼですってば！
♪♪～
あぶねえな ﾊﾞｶ野郎
貧乏人どもが➡
That was close, moron!
Poor people shouldn't be wandering around in a place where they don't belong!
場違いな所で
ｳﾛｳﾛしてんじゃねえぞ！
ﾍｯ ざまあみやがれってんだ
目障りなんだよ！
Heh, serves you right.
Damn eyesore.
待てよ 今ｱﾝﾀ
わざとぶつかったな｡
Hold on.
You bumped into her on purpose.
謝れよ ちゃんと姉上に謝れ！
Apologize.
Apologize to Sis!
なんだ？ ｸｿｶﾞｷ｡
What's that, little brat?
やめて 新ちゃん｡
Stop it, Shin-chan.
What? It's them again?
なあに また ｱｲﾂらよ｡
What is it this time?
今度は 何 ｹﾝｶ？
本当 はた迷惑な連中ね｡
A fight?
They're such a nuisance.
帰れ 場違いなんだよ お前ら！
Get lost! You don't belong here!
ここは お前らみたいなのが
来ていい場所じゃないんだよ！
This isn't a place for freaks like you!
そうだ 帰れ！
帰れ 貧乏人！
Yeah! Get lost!
Get lost, poor people!
Cut it out already!
ﾌﾝ だそうだ｡
There you have it.
It appears that you're the ones at fault, not me.
どうやら 悪者は ｵﾚじゃなく
お前らのほうらしい｡
I won't leave!
帰らない！
お前が謝るまで ﾎﾞｸは帰らないぞ！
I won't leave until you apologize!
Shinpachi.
新八｡
(東城)帰っていただけませんか？
I must ask that you leave.
これ以上
若の顔に泥を塗るまねは➡
I, Ayumu Tojo, one of the four heavenly kings of Yagyu, will not permit
この柳生四天王が一人
東城歩が 許しません｡
any further behavior that would besmirch the young master's honor.
そうだ！
貧乏人は 帰れ！
That's right!
Poor people should get lost!
わかったか 早く帰れ！
ﾜﾊﾊ！
Got it?
Make yourself scarce already!
うお～！
私は 若の友人たちを
侮辱した連中に➡
I was talking to the people insulting the young master's friends.
出ていけと言ったのですよ｡
東城さん｡
Tojo-san...
ｷｻﾏ 誕生日を祝いに来てやった
客に対して何だ その言い草は！
You bastard!
How can you say that to the guests you invited to a birthday celebration?!
柳生一門とて
捨て置けぬぞ 今の言葉！
Those words will lead to the fall of the Yagyu clan!
お客？ こちらから来てくれと
頼んだ覚えは ありませんがね｡
Guests?
I don't recall inviting you.
私が
この生誕祭にお呼びしたのは➡
The only people I've invited to this celebration
この 若のご友人方だけです｡
are the young master's friends.
他の者は どこから➡
The other people merely take the effort to show up every year.
甘いにおいを嗅ぎつけてきたのか｡
Enticed by the sweet smell, I suppose.
毎年毎年 頼みもせぬのに
ぞろぞろと ご苦労さまですな｡
しかし 生憎
若は お父上とは違い➡
Unfortunately, the young master, unlike her father, places friendship before money.
金の縁より
心の縁を大切にするお方｡
You won't be able to build your superficial relationships with the young master.
貴殿らが望むような関係は
築けますまいよ｡
ええ～い！
興が冷めたわ！
Bah! You've lost my interest!
Remember this well.
覚えておれ！
我らに こんな恥をかかせて➡
You won't get off lightly for embarrassing us like this.
ただで済むと思うな！
This is the last time the renowned Yagyu clan will be getting on its high horse.
名門 柳生流とて➡
調子に乗っていられるのも
今のうちよ！
It'll fall into ruin without our backing.
我らの力なしでは
いずれ零落していこうて！
Tojo-san.
東城さん すみません！
I'm very sorry!
ﾎﾞｸらを かばったばかりに
こんな とんでもないこと…！
Everything's been ruined because you were defending us...
いえいえ｡ かばったなど
めっそうもない｡
え？
Not at all...
I wasn't defending you.
The renowned Yagyu clan has many connections.
名門 柳生流ともなれば
しがらみもたくさんあります｡
There was a reason for mowing the lawn here.
雑草を刈るにも
理由がいるのです｡
It just so happened that some bugs happened to conveniently pop out as well.
虫などわいてくれれば
実に都合がいい｡
それって…｡
いやはや｡
You mean...
Indeed, I knew that you people would snap back without thinking.
あなたたちなら考えなしに➡
必ず 食いついてくれると
思いましたよ｡
You made the task so much simpler.
いや～ 実に刈りやすかった｡
Now our lawn is all neat and tidy.
おかげで庭が
きれいになりましたよ｡
東城さん ｱﾝﾀひょっとして
ﾎﾞｸらを利用したんですか!?
Tojo-san...
Were you using us?
Using us to instigate those people...!
ﾎﾞｸらをけしかけて
あの人たちを…！
ﾊｯﾊｯﾊｯﾊｯ！
さて どうですかな｡
Who knows?
Hey! Hold it right there!
おい 待てｺﾗ！
糸目 おいっ!!
Damn slit eyes!
東城｡
かっこつけるのも結構だが➡
Tojo, I don't mind you putting on airs,
ﾊﾟﾊﾟ上に叱られても
ﾎﾞｸは 知らんからな｡
but don't come crying when Father yells at you.
ともあれ 礼は言っておく｡
Nevertheless, you have my gratitude.
♪♪～
Thank you for such a wonderful birthday.
(九兵衛)ｽﾃｷな誕生日を
ありがとう｡
[Preview]
Gin-san...
It's been a long time...
It's been three years of my life falling apart since this anime began...
But next week...
The next episode...
"The Other Side of the Other Side of the Other Side would be the Other Side."
I'll finally graduate from being a DORK.
[An all-out battle to finally end the downward spiral of DORKness!!]
[Taizo Hasegawa (38 years old), with the love for his wife clutched in his bosom, refuses to lose this time around!]
[See you next time.]